{"tossups": [{"question": "One character in this play commands \"Out, vile jelly,\" in reference to a character that says, \u201cAs flies to wanton boys are we to the gods.\u201d In this play, one character calls himself \u201cTom O\u2019Bedlam\u201d after being robbed of his birthright. The King of France (*) marries a character in this play despite her being disinherited. Another character in this play tries to commit suicide, but his son Edgar saves him by leading him off an imaginary cliff. For ten points, name this Shakespearean play about the titular king who divided his kingdom between two thankless daughters, Goneril and Regan, and cast out his youngest daughter Cordelia.", "answer": "King Lear", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The Denkard contains information about one sect of this religion. When an adherent of this religion dies, their soul is taken to either the House of Song or the House of Lies after crossing the Chinvat Bridge. In this religion, dead bodies are often placed on Towers of Silence, and adherents of this religion worship at (*) fire temples. The sacred text of this religion is called the Avesta. For 10 points, name this religion that centers around the conflict between the god Ahura Mazda and the evil spirit Ahriman and is named after an ancient Persian prophet.", "answer": "Zoroastrianism (accept Zarathustrianism, accept Mazdayasna)", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Probes in this lab technique have index codes of x-prime, y-prime, and z-prime, and are used to determine the Rohrschneider and McReynolds constants. An equation for organic compounds used in this lab technique linearly relates the log of t sub r and the number of carbon atoms in a molecule to determine the (*) Kov\u00e1ts retention index. The theoretical plate height of this process can be determined using the van Deemter equation. The \u201cpartition\u201d form of this technique modifies the thin-layer type, which uses a silica gel stationary phase. For 10 points, name this lab technique that can be used to separate pigments.", "answer": "chromatography (accept gas chromatography)", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The Washington Post criticized one candidate from this state for leaving Justin Fairfax\u2019s name off some campaign literature. Mark Herring was recently reelected Attorney General in this state and Danica Roem defeated Robert Marshall to become this state\u2019s first openly (*) transgender legislator. A campaign ad in this state attempted to tie one candidate to the gang MS-13, while turnout in this state\u2019s November 2017 election was influenced by violence in its city of Charlottesville. For ten points, name this U.S. state where Ralph Northam defeated Ed Gillespie in a recent gubernatorial election.", "answer": "Commonwealth of Virginia", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "Apollodorus of Damascus criticized the size of statues in a temple designed by this man. This notable philhellene created the Panhellenion League of city-states, and early in this man\u2019s reign he executed four consuls including Lucius Quietus. This emperor sponsored the cult of his deceased lover (*) Antinous who drowned while with this man on one of his many travels. This husband of Vibia Sabina controversially evacuated most of the territory seized by his predecessor Trajan. For ten points, name this third of the Five Good Emperors with a namesake wall in Britain.", "answer": "Publius Aelius Hadrianus Augustus", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Some types of these organisms produce compounds with antibacterial properties called sceptrin and ageliferin. Cyanobacteria cause the rust-colored bands in Aplysina red band syndrome, a contagious disease that affects members of this phylum. Body systems of this phylum include asconoid, syconoid, and leuconoid. One variety of this organism belonging to the class (*) Hexactinellida has silicon spicules and is known as the \u201cglass\u201d type. In these organisms, water is absorbed through the osculum. Flattened pinacocytes and nutrient-filtering choanocytes are cells bound to the jelly-like mesohyl of these organisms. For 10 points, name this phylum of sessile invertebrates also known as sponges.", "answer": "Porifera (accept sponges before mention)", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This man identified sacred\u2013profane dichotomy as the distinguishing characteristic of religion and claimed that God was \u201csociety, writ large.\u201d This thinker emphasized the scientific nature of social science by advocating for specific and objective study, and noted the coercive power of social facts. This man\u2019s first major work described how means of maintaining social order varied in The (*) Division of Labor in Society. In his most famous work, this man divided a certain action into fatalistic, altruistic, egoistic, and anomic occurrences. For 10 points, name this eminent French sociologist and author of Suicide.", "answer": "Emile Durkheim", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This battle was preceded by St. Leger\u2019s expedition and the Battle of Bennington. Ebenezer Learned and Enoch Poor commanded troops in this battle, during which George and James Clinton\u2019s diversionary attacks proved fruitless. An uncredited statue of a boot commemorates one hero of this battle, in which Timothy Murphy fatally wounded (*) Simon Fraser. Bloody fighting at Bemis Heights and Freeman\u2019s Farm in this battle forced the surrender of 6,000 starving British soldiers led by \"Gentleman Johnny\" Burgoyne. For ten points, name this 1777 American victory credited with turning the tide in the Revolutionary War.", "answer": "Battle of Saratoga", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This author wrote that \u201cthe she-bear thus accosted rends the peasant tooth\u201d in his poem \u201cThe Female of the Species.\u201d In a short story by this author, Taffimai Metallumi delivers a picture message to her mother. This author wrote of a \u201clazarushian-leather\u201d man serving (*) water to English soldiers in Gunga Din, and in this man\u2019s most famous work, the speaker recounts a hypothetical game of pitch-and-toss and ends by saying \u201cyou\u2019ll be a man my son!\u201d For ten points, name this author of Just So Stories, The Jungle Book, and If.", "answer": "Rudyard Kipling", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A method of testing for this condition named for Solovay and Strassen capitalizes on the efficiency of calculating the Jacobi symbol. An Ulam spiral examines patterns in the occurrence of this property, and numbers with this property can be generated using the Sieve of Atkins or the Sieve of (*) Eratosthenes. RSA cryptography relies on the difficulty of finding factors with this property. A group of numbers of the form 2^n-1 that have this property is named for Mersenne; that group contains the largest number known to have this property. For 10 points, name this condition of numbers that have exactly two positive integer divisors.", "answer": "primality (accept being prime or equivalents) HALFTIME", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The Mycenaean \u201chouse sanctuaries\u201d are thought to have been dedicated to this deity. This figure turned Tiresias into a woman when he struck a pair of snakes with a stick. This deity offered Hebe to Heracles as his bride, and Nephele was created to resemble this deity. This goddess offered Paris (*) control over all of Europe and Asia, and she indirectly caused Semele to burst into flames. Heracles killed two snakes that were sent by this goddess to kill him because she was jealous. For 10 points, name this wife of Zeus, the chief goddess of the Greek pantheon.", "answer": "Hera (do not accept or prompt on \u201cJuno\u201d)", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "One formulation of this law states that the closed line integral of the heat absorbed by the system over temperature is less than or equal to zero. Loschmidt's paradox arises from a statement of this law that breaks time-reversal symmetry known as (*) Boltzmann\u2019s H-theorem. This law states that heat cannot spontaneously flow from a colder object to a warmer object. A thought experiment that would violate this law involves the opening and closing of a gate to allow particles of different speeds through, that is Maxwell\u2019s Demon. For 10 points, name this law that states that the entropy of a closed system cannot decrease.", "answer": "second law of thermodynamics", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One character in the novel introduces himself as William Thompson from Ohio, a person stopping on his way to visit his uncle. In this novel, two families who detest each other attend church together and hold their rifles between their knees as the minister preaches about brotherly love. Those families are the (*) Shepherdsons and the Grangerfords. The protagonist of this novel fakes his death by killing a pig in order to escape his father, Pap. In this novel the Royal Nonesuch is performed by the Duke and the Dauphin. For ten points, name this Mark Twain novel about the title character\u2019s journey down the Mississippi river with a slave named Jim.", "answer": "The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Attempts to weaken this government included the Battle of Dakar and the Attack on Mers-el-K\u00e9bir. The Vel\u2019 d\u2019Hiv raids were carried out by this state\u2019s paramilitary wing, the Milice, and this state\u2019s creation was opposed by 80 members of Parliament including Leon Blum. This government embraced the motto (*) \u201cWork, Family, Fatherland,\u201d and maintained the infamous Gurs and Drancy internment camps. Succeeding the Third Republic, this state was led by Pierre Laval and Philippe P\u00e9tain. For ten points, name this Nazi puppet government which ruled France during World War II.", "answer": "Vichy France", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The orange tree in the background of this painting has not yet produced fruit, symbolizing the potential of this work\u2019s main figure. Charles Mack controversially described this painting as a piece of Medici propaganda, and the action of this painting likely occurs on the island of Cythera. The nymph (*) Chloris is being carried toward the central figure of this painting by the wind god Zephyr. On the right side of this painting, the goddess Pomona holds a billowing orange cloth. For ten points, name this painting by Sandro Botticelli depicting a nude goddess rising out of the ocean on a seashell.", "answer": "The Birth of Venus (or Nascita di Venere)", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This empire was chronicled by the diplomat Megasthenes, who commented on its respect for foreigners. This empire overthrew the Magadhan Kingdom, and the Arthashastra was compiled by Chanakya during this its early years. Succeeded by the Shunga Dynasty, this empire repulsed an invasion from the burgeoning (*) Seleucid Empire, and art from this empire often featured four lions. The greatest ruler of this empire famously converted to Buddhism in penance for his initiation of the Kalinga War. For ten points, name this sprawling ancient empire of Ashoka and Chandragupta, the largest in Indian history.", "answer": "Mauryan Empire (do not accept or prompt on \u201cGupta Empire\u201d)", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This work incorporates music from a traditional circle dance called \u201cKhorovod\u201d in its \u201cRounds\u201d section. This work features syncopated E-flat dominant seventh chords in one section and later transitions to the \u201cProcession of the Sage\u201d. Several Lithuanian folk songs are quoted in this work\u2019s first part entitled (*) \u201cAdoration of the Earth\u201d which opens with a bassoon playing above high C. Chords spelling out the word \u201cdead\u201d follow a scene entitled \u201cSacrificial Dance\u201d in this ballet where a girl\u2019s neck is snapped during a pagan ritual. For 10 points, name this ballet written by Igor Stravinsky that caused a riot at its Paris premiere.", "answer": "The Rite of Spring (or Le Sacre du printemps or Vesna svyashchennaya)", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Audiovisual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a short story by this author, a narrator feels a gentle hand on his shoulder after seeing a pack of dogs and panicking. That story is about a man who goes mad after his son with a brain hernia dies. In one novel by this man, 15 boys are trapped, and so are a korean boy named Li and a girl who dies of (*) plague after being bitten by a dog. The title sound of a novel by this author is made when a cucumber is shoved up the anus of Mitsusaburo\u2019s friend. For ten points, name this author who wrote The Silent Cry and wrote about his autistic son Hikari in A Personal Matter.", "answer": "Kenzaburo Oe", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This location includes the Washington Column and Lost Arrow rock formations, and Galen Clark spent 24 years as the guardian of this place. Glacier Point sits 2,500 feet above Half Dome in this location. One damming project in this place\u2019s Hetch Hetchy Valley was opposed by John (*) Muir. This park can be seen from the Tunnel View, which offers a stunning view of its namesake waterfall. Ansel Adams took many famous photographs of this park\u2019s El Capitan monolith. For ten points, name this national park in the Sierra Nevadas of eastern California.", "answer": "Yosemite National Park", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "This artist\u2019s Russian Schoolroom shows young students looking at a bust of Vladimir Lenin, while his The Rookie depicts the Red Sox locker room. The letters \u201cKKK\u201d and a racial slur appear behind Ruby Bridges in one of this artist\u2019s works which reacts to New Orleans school desegregation and is entitled (*) The Problem We All Live With. A woman serves a turkey dinner in this man\u2019s Freedom from Want, part of his \u201cFour Freedoms\u201d series. For 10 points, name this 20th century American artist who painted many scenes of everyday life life as covers for the Saturday Evening Post.", "answer": "Norman Rockwell", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A work predating Bram Stoker\u2019s Dracula by 26 years describes a vampire who has this trait, Carmilla. A character who displays this trait clings to a picture of a European knight, who turns out to be Joan of Arc. This trait is exhibited by Randolph and Joel in Other Voices, Other Rooms. The poem (*) \u201cPhainetai Moi\u201d describes this trait in its poet, who was known as \u201cthe tenth muse.\u201d De Profundis was written as a philosophical work for Lord Alfred Douglass during time one possessor of this trait spent in Reading Gaol. For ten points, name this trait exhibited by Yukio Mishima, Truman Capote, Sappho, and Oscar Wilde.", "answer": "homosexuality (accept close equivalents like gay, lesbian, or queer) Bonuses", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "This protein is abundant in the extracellular matrix of bone tissue. For ten points each:", "answers": ["collagen", "triple helix", "phosphates (accept PO43\u2212)"], "parts": ["Name this most common protein in mammals.", "Collagen possesses this geometric structure, which was erroneously proposed as the structure for DNA by Pauling and Corey.", "One reason the triple helix structure of DNA was rejected was because these anions repel each other, preventing the three chains from staying together."], "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This man uses the term <em>Aufheben</em> to describe the interaction between two competing arguments, the thesis and the antithesis. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel", "geist (prompt on \u201cspirit\u201d)", "Francis Fukuyama"], "parts": ["Name this thinker who described his namesake dialectic in Science of Logic and wrote Phenomenology of Spirit.", "In Phenomenology of Spirit, Hegel used this term to describe the force which moves great historical figures to change the course of the world.", "This American thinker observed the overpowering democratic geist of the modern era and predicted its inevitable dominance in his 1992 book The End of History and the Last Man."], "category": "Philosophy"}, {"leadin": "This show\u2019s corporate Pixies were voiced by Nixon speechwriter and Montgomery Blair alumnus Ben Stein. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Fairly OddParents", "Vicky", "Poof"], "parts": ["Name this Nickelodeon cartoon about Timmy Turner and his two magical companions.", "In the Fairly OddParents, Timmy is tormented by this sadistic baby-sitter. Chip Skylark writes a song describing this character as icky.", "In a 2008 special, Timmy\u2019s fairy godfather Cosmo gave birth to this baby fairy. Unlike other fairies who use wands, this magical infant grants wishes with a rattle."], "category": "Trash"}, {"leadin": "Name some literary movements from the past three centuries. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Sturm und Drang", "Gothic fiction", "Beat Generation"], "parts": ["The prominence of this late 1700s German movement was ended when Goethe and Schiller transitioned to Weimar Classicism. Its name is usually translated as \u201cStorm and Stress.\u201d", "Horace Walpole\u2019s The Castle of Otranto is considered to be the first novel of this movement, whose other novels like Mary Shelley\u2019s Frankenstein demonstrate its elements of gloom and fear. Its name comes from a style of architecture.", "This 1950s American movement was closely intertwined with the counterculture of the time. Its prominent members include Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac."], "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "During this conflict, France sided with her traditional Protestant enemies to counter Habsburg encroachment. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Thirty Years\u2019 War", "defenestration (or being thrown out of a window)", "Battle of White Mountain"], "parts": ["Name this massively destructive religious war which decimated much of Central Europe in the seventeenth century. It was ended by the Peace of Westphalia", "The Thirty Years\u2019 War began after this action was inflicted on two Catholic emissaries of Emperor Ferdinand II in Prague. Unlike a similar event in 1419, none of those targeted for this action died.", "This 1620 battle during the Thirty Years\u2019 War was a major victory for Ferdinand II and the Catholic League, but its potential impact incited more Protestants nations to join the fray."], "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This work begins with a pianissimo adagio sostenuto in triplets, echoing a \u201cmournful ghostly voice.\u201d For ten points each:", "answers": ["Moonlight Sonata (accept Piano Sonata No. 14; or Opus 27, No. 2)", "Domenico Scarlatti", "F. A. E. Sonata"], "parts": ["Name this work by Beethoven named for a phenomenon shining on Lake Lucerne.", "This baroque composer was known for his 555 keyboard sonatas, although he composed in other forms as well.", "This four-movement sonata for piano and violin was a collaborative work between Robert Schumann, Johannes Brahms, and Albert Dietrich. It was named for a German phrase meaning \u201cfree but lonely.\u201d"], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about the letter r in science. For ten points each:", "answers": ["r\u00f6ntgen", "Rydberg constant", "ideal gases"], "parts": ["This unit, symbolized with a capital R, was formerly used to measure exposure to gamma and x-rays, which were discovered by its namesake.", "This constant, symbolized R-sub-H for hydrogen, appears in its formulator\u2019s equation for calculating the wavelength of Lyman and Balmer lines.", "R is a constant in the equation PV equals nRT, which describes these theoretical substances that are not impacted by intermolecular forces."], "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This man maintained a public dispute with Jun'ichir\u014d Tanizaki. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Akutagawa Ry\u016bnosuke", "In a Grove (or Yabu no Naka)", "a comb and a rope"], "parts": ["Name this author of \u201cHana\u201d and \u201cRash\u014dmon\u201d who names the highest Japanese award for literature.", "This Akutagawa work follows a murder from the perspectives of a woodcutter, a buddhist priest, a homen, a criminal, a girl, and the ghost of the dead man, Takehiro.", "These two items are found next to Takehiro by the woodcutter; name either. One of these items is not mentioned by any other character, and one is used to bind Takehiro."], "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "A 1946 riot in this prison required mortar fire and two platoons of Marines to subdue. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary", "Al Capone", "John and Clarence Anglin"], "parts": ["Name this notoriously inescapable federal prison in San Francisco Bay, nicknamed \u201cThe Rock.\u201d", "Perhaps the most famous Alcatraz inmate was this Chicago gangster and bootlegger who spent four and a half years at Alcatraz after being convicted of tax evasion.", "Though Alcatraz was supposedly escape proof, Frank Morris and these brothers attempted to escape The Rock in a prison-made boat in 1962. The actual fate of Morris and these brothers remains unknown. Note: Last name sufficient."], "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "This man created many paintings of figures from the court of Henry VIII. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Hans Holbein the Younger (prompt on Hans Holbein, do not accept \u201cHans Holbein the Elder\u201d)", "pomegranate", "Salvador Dali"], "parts": ["Name this artist of Body of Dead Christ in the Tomb along with a depiction of two men with a globe, astrolabe, and lute in The Ambassadors.", "Holbein painted \u201cVirgin and Child\u201d with this fruit. Sandro Botticelli created multiple works with this fruit, including a famous Madonna of this fruit.", "This artist's Dream Caused by the Flight of a Bee prominently features a pomegranate. He created elephants with spider-thin legs in his Swans Reflecting Elephants."], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"leadin": "Soviet intervention saved this country from losing territory to Somalia in the Ogaden War. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Ethiopia", "Derg (or Dergue)", "Eritrea"], "parts": ["Name this East African nation, which suffered a terrible famine in the mid 1980s and was earlier ruled by Haile Selassie.", "Ethiopia fell under this regime following the deposition of Haile Selassie. Led by Mengistu Haile Mariam, this communist dictatorship killed hundreds of thousands of people in the Qey Shibir terror.", "The Derg frequently battled separatists from this region, which achieved independence from Ethiopia in 1993. Today, sporadic violence persists between Ethiopia and this country."], "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "These creatures are known as ceasg in Scotland, rusalkas in Eastern Europe, and maneli in Ancient Persia. For ten points each:", "answers": ["mermaids", "selkies (accept selchies)", "ningyos"], "parts": ["Name these mythological beings generally imagined with the torso of a woman and the tail of a fish.", "These Celtic maidens of the sea often marry the men who steal their seal skins, at least until they can return to the water.", "These Japanese \u201cmermaids\u201d are often depicted as hideous creatures, but those who catch and eat them are said to have eternal youth and a long life."], "category": "Mythology"}, {"leadin": "This system is complemented by interpretation and jurisprudence known as <em>fiqh</em>. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Sharia (or Sharia law)", "ijtihad", "fatwa"], "parts": ["Name this legal system based on Islamic teachings. Many contemporary groups support this legal system, despite its controversial hudud punishments.", "Within Sharia, this term denoted the process of reaching legal decisions when the Qur'an or Hadith are unclear. The \u201cgates\u201d of this process were supposedly closed in the 10th century.", "Legal opinions derived from Sharia are known by this term. Ayatollah Khomeini called for the execution of Salman Rushdie in one of these rulings in 1989."], "category": "Religion"}, {"leadin": "For ten points each, name some notable authors and poets who achieved African American literary firsts.", "answers": ["Toni Morrison", "Phillis Wheatley", "Olaudah Equiano"], "parts": ["This author became the first African American to win the Nobel Prize in Literature for novels such as Beloved and Song of Solomon.", "This poet was the first African American woman to have her work, specifically Poems on Various Subjects, Religious and Moral, published.", "This man wrote one of the first widely disseminated slave narratives, an autobiography billed as an \u201cInteresting Narrative\u201d of this man\u2019s life."], "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "These entities can be multiplied if the number of columns in the first one is equal to the number of rows in the second. For ten points each:", "answers": ["matrices (or matrix)", "expansion by minors", "Cramer\u2019s rule"], "parts": ["Name these rectangular arrays of numbers.", "The determinant of a matrix can be found by this method, which requires finding the determinants of matrices left after crossing out a row and a column. When the namesake entities are multiplied by 1 or negative 1, the resulting values are called cofactors.", "This rule is used to find solutions to systems of linear equations written as a matrix. It expresses each solution as a quotient of two determinants."], "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "After the characters of this play leave their Estate for the last time, they leave the servant Firs to die. For ten points each:", "answers": ["The Cherry Orchard (or Vishnevyi sad)", "The Seagull (or Chayka)", "the Lawyer"], "parts": ["Name this play by Chekhov about the purchase of Madame Ranevsky\u2019s estate and the subsequent cutting down of the title area.", "This other Chekhov work ends with the suicide of Constantine Treplev after Nina reveals her love for Trigorin. This play takes its name from a certain beachside pest.", "In Chekhov's \u201cThe Bet,\u201d this character volunteers to live in solitary confinement for 15 years as part of the title bet."], "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about patriotic songs in history. For ten points each:", "answers": ["\u201cLa Marseillaise\u201d", "Germany", "\u201cGuantanamera\u201d"], "parts": ["This revolutionary song was written to celebrate an upcoming war with Austria and Prussia, and today is France\u2019s national anthem. It urges \u201cTo arms, citizens\u201d and calls for \u201cimpure blood\u201d to soak French fields.", "\u201cDas Lied der Deutschen\u201d is the national anthem of this nation, but that song\u2019s original lyrics demanding continental domination were removed following World War Two.", "Jos\u00e9 Mart\u00ed wrote the poetic lyrics of this song amidst the Cuban War of Independence. The Sandpipers sang a notable version of this song, which remains widely popular in Cuba."], "category": "History"}, {"leadin": "The lyricist of this duo mentored Stephen Sondheim. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Rodgers and Hammerstein", "Carousel", "The Sound of Music"], "parts": ["Name this artistic duo from the \u201cGolden Age of Musical Theater\u201d who created such hits as Oklahoma, South Pacific, and the The King and I.", "This second musical by Rodgers and Hammerstein premiered in 1945. This show profiled the ill-fated romance of Julie Jordan and Billy Bigelow and contained songs like \u201cIf I Loved You\u201d and \u201cYou\u2019ll Never Walk Alone.\u201d", "This final Rodgers and Hammerstein musical opened in 1959 and became a box office hit six years later. In this show, Maria leaves an abbey to tutor the Von Trapp children."], "category": "Trash"}, {"leadin": "Not all urban areas come into being organically. For ten points each:", "answers": ["Canberra", "Bras\u00edlia", "Pierre Charles l'Enfant"], "parts": ["This capital of Australia was designed as a \u201cgarden city\u201d by architects Walter and Marion Griffin. Its location arose from a compromise between Melbourne and Sydney.", "Like Canberra, this Brazilian capital was pre-planned. Designed by L\u00facio Costa and Oscar Niemeyer, this fourth largest city in Brazil is carefully divided into sectors based on utility.", "Perhaps the world\u2019s most famous planned city is Washington DC, designed by this French engineer. This man mapped out the city\u2019s \u201cgrand avenues,\u201d and a major DC plaza is named for him."], "category": "Geography"}, {"leadin": "Answer the following questions about a certain explosive chain reaction. For ten points each:", "answers": ["nuclear fission (prompt on \u201cnuclear reaction\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \u201cnuclear fusion\u201d)", "neutron", "uranium-235 (accept U-235 ; do not accept or prompt on \u201curanium\u201d or \u201curanium-238\u201d or \u201curanium-239\u201d)"], "parts": ["Name this process discovered by Otto Hahn and Fritz Strassman which enabled the creation of atomic weaponry.", "Nuclear fission is initiated by the absorption of this sub-atomic particle, which causes the nucleus of an atom to become unstable and fission. The resulting reaction releases both energy and more of these particles.", "To create a traditional, non-plutonium nuclear weapon, a core must be enriched in this fissile isotope until it constitutes about 90%. In the Manhattan Project, gaseous diffusion was used to enrich it, although today centrifuges are more common."], "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "The charge of this subatomic particle was determined by the Millikan oil drop experiment. For ten points each:", "answers": ["electron", "de Broglie wavelength", "David Bohm"], "parts": ["Name this particle that carries negative charge.", "This property of an electron is equal to Planck\u2019s constant divided by its momentum. This is the wavelength associated with a massive particle.", "Louis de Broglie names a causal interpretation of quantum mechanics with this physicist, whose namesake mechanics involves particles accompanied by pilot waves."], "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}]}